Every 6 months software engineering or
at least the coding part of it is 6
months from being dead. I am sure you've
heard this narrative too many times
before. It's a pattern that has repeated
itself the last couple of years. Like
right here we have Dario, the CEO of
Anthropic, who I I do respect a lot by
the way, but he went on the record March
of last year saying that AI would be
writing 90% of code in 6 months. And
then comes 6 months later in September,
of course it is not even close. And then
he goes on the record literally just a
week ago again saying that software
engineers could go extinct this year in
2026 and it's going to be painful for a
lot of people. So he's said things like
this before, but this time guys, it's
actually going to happen, right? Well,
we'll see. We'll see what happens this
year. And Dario is far from alone. All
of the leaders in the tech industry are
saying things like this. Like Jensen
Huang saying kids shouldn't even learn
to code all the way back in 2024. The
Amazon Cloud CEO saying most engineers
won't even be coding. Of course we have
Sam Altman saying mastering AI tools is
the new learn to code. The Microsoft AI
CEO even going so far as to say this
year that within a year and a half all
white collar tasks will be automated. So
crazy claims that honestly I think are
pretty exaggerated and a lot of these
tech leaders are very biased in what
they're saying and honestly I think
living in a bubble.
So right now I just want to have a
candid conversation with you. Let's look
at the data and think about why are
these tech leaders so biased and living
in a bubble? What does this mean for us?
What's the true power of AI coding
assistants? Because there is a lot of
stock in what they're saying, but
there's just a massive difference
between the capabilities of AI coding
assistants and true adoption, especially
at an enterprise level. We'll cover that
as well. And I never explicitly ask for
comments on a YouTube video, but right
now I am cuz I really want to hear from
you. What do you think about all this?
And if you think I'm wrong on any
account here. Like if I'm
misinterpreting any data, if your
experience is different from mine, cuz
we're going to look at the data. I'll
talk about my experiences, put that all
together, and talk about what that means
for us going forward as well. Now,
here's the thing. I am not saying that
coding agents aren't powerful enough to
replace most coding. I've done that for
myself. I've built this system. So,
coding agents are powerful enough. There
is a lot of stock in what these tech
leaders are saying, but there are two
huge caveats that I feel like they're
dismissing way too much. First of all, I
have seen firsthand how low the adoption
of these tools is at an enterprise
level. You would be surprised cuz I
teach both individuals and teams at
larger companies how to leverage AI
coding assistants effectively. And there
is so much resistance in these larger
companies that I just think there's no
way, even within 5 years, most companies
will be using AI coding assistants to
write 90% of code. And then the other
big caveat here is there's so much more
to software engineering than just
coding. And these skills, I think, are
never going to go away. Maybe you've
heard the new term intent engineering
showing up on the internet recently.
It's really just a lot of software
engineering principles put into a
package to apply to AI, and people are
recognizing that we still need these
skills even as coding agents are getting
more and more powerful.
So, I could have made this video even a
year ago, but what really put me over
the edge to make it right now is a
couple of comments that Boris Cherny
made in some podcasts that people are
taking the wrong way. So, he was on the
Y Combinator and Lenny podcast, and in
both he said that coding is a largely
solved. Now, if you watch both these
podcasts, which they are great, and you
really get into what Boris is saying, I
can get behind it. But when you take
this at face value, coding is largely
solved, it's a very exaggerated claim
that a lot of people are misinterpreting
thinking that software engineering is
dying and that he's saying the same
thing as Dario. But he literally
clarified later on X that software
engineering is still very important. He
said, and I quote, "Someone has to
prompt the clouds, talk to the
customers. This is very important.
Coordinate with other teams, decide what
to build next. Engineering is changing
and great engineers are more important
than ever. And so, looking at this right
now, and Boris he's the creator of
Claude code. So, Dario is the CEO saying
something that seems very, very
contradictory. Software engineering is
going to go extinct in 2026. Software
engineering is more important than ever.
So, how do you wrestle with this? I
mean, these contradictions, even within
the same company, is why I'm very
confident in saying that these people
are living in bubbles and they're very
biased in what they are saying. And all
you have to do here is just follow the
money. I mean, it's a pretty simple
argument. Like if we look at Anthropic
here, they went from a $61.5 billion
valuation to a whopping $380 billion in
less than a year. And so, yeah, Dario is
benefiting a lot when people are leaning
more and more into AI coding assistants
instead of writing code themselves and
trying to be software engineers. And so,
that you have this whole narrative of
like, don't even get a computer science
degree. That's very helpful for people
like Dario, also people like Jensen. So,
yeah, his net worth was only $3 billion
in 2019. And then this is pretty
outdated, but even in 2024 it was
already at $90 billion. Just insane. And
this makes sense. Nvidia is selling the
chips, most of the chips for LLM
training and inference. So, he is also
benefiting a lot. And then, oh yeah, of
course, Sam Altman just as another good
example here. OpenAI is valued at over
$730 billion now. And by the way, Sam is
in line for a 7% equity stake that is
going to be worth over $10 billion. So,
he's doing pretty good for himself with
this whole AI craze right now.
So, with all of that being said, the
truth right now really seems like yes,
software engineering is going to evolve
significantly over the next couple of
years, but it is not going away. Maybe
we will need less engineers, but the
role is still going to be very
important. And also, AI is not going to
be writing 90% or more of code for most
companies. We'll get there eventually,
but not like this, not in the next year.
Now, allow me to share some of my own
personal experience here, cuz I have a
lot of it that I think will really tie
this together. Cuz I went from being
that engineer that refused to use AI
coding tools to now teaching thousands
of individuals and teams at large
companies how to use them effectively.
So, back in 2024, I was one of those
people that said no to all AI coding
tools. I wrote all of my code by hand
still. But finally, November of 2024 is
when I installed Win Surf. That was my
first AI coding assistant, and man was
my brain blown. Like I wish I had used
AI coding assistants for the last year.
And so, I didn't start doing a ton with
these AI coding assistants. Like they
just helped me with writing a function
or editing a single file. But over time,
like the next 6 months, I built up my
full system that I call my Pivotal Loop,
plan, implement, validate. I have a
video on my channel where I cover it
that I'll link to right here. So, I've
gotten to the point now where I delegate
all of my coding, at least almost all of
my coding to the AI coding assistants
because I put myself in the driver seat
for the planning and the validation at
the end, sandwiching the implementation.
So, I'm not vibe coding. I'm still doing
everything a software engineer does,
right? I define the architecture and
tech stack. I take requirements and
translate that into the context for the
coding agent. I do a lot of code
reviewing and even fixing code by hand
still. But I am using AI coding
assistants as a primary driver. Like I
said, there is a lot of stock in what
these tech leaders are saying because
the tools definitely are capable enough.
That's not the problem. The problem is
these exaggerated claims saying that all
companies are going to adopt them, AI
coding assistants are going to write all
code in the next year. That's what I
think is really not the truth here. So,
there are two more big things that I
want to cover right now, both of which
I'm confident you can get behind. The
first is that AI coding assistants still
require an insane amount of guidance to
get the job done reliably. Like Boris
said, the role of software engineer that
you have to take on is is important than
ever. The other thing is you would be
surprised what adoption of coding agents
looks like at an enterprise level. I
talked about this a little bit already,
but I'll share more my experience and a
lot of data that I found to back up what
I have seen. So, both of these things
pointing to the fact that all of these
claims on the internet right now are
very exaggerated.
So, let's start with the argument for
software engineers. And honestly, the
best way to quickly explain why we need
to be a software engineer so much still
is to look at the evolution of prompt
engineering, to context engineering,
then to the new intent engineering. So,
prompt engineering, you've probably
heard of this before. It's been around
for a few years now. It's really just
the art of wording things in the best
way possible for the LLM to get the best
single output. And so, this doesn't
really look like software engineering at
all. It's really just wording things in
the right way to LLMs. But then last
year, this evolved to context
engineering. So, this is sort of a
direct evolution of prompt engineering
because we're going from single inputs
to get single outputs to creating this
entire system of context for our AI
agents, especially AI coding assistants,
giving them all of the context they need
to plausibly solve the task at hand. So,
it's a lot more detailed, and this is
starting to look more like software
engineering cuz a big part of the
context ecosystem that we provide is
going to be things like the
architecture, the tech stack, the key
decisions that we made around the
feature or app that we want to build.
It's starting to feel like everything
except for the coding is our
responsibility because we are the ones
doing the context engineering for the
agents. And then more recently, this has
evolved to intent engineering. Now, I'm
not just trying to throw buzzwords at
you here. I'm trying to make a point of
how we are evolving more and more over
time to how we work these coding agents
to sit more as that senior engineer
role. So, the idea with intent
engineering, and Nate B. Jones covers
this on his YouTube channel and his
podcast. It's really good stuff, but the
idea with intent engineering is not only
do we want to give good context around
our code base and things like that. We
also want to be very clear on things
like the success criteria, how the agent
can validate its own work, making sure
we're super aligned on what we're
building. So that not only is the code
correct, but that the application or
feature is actually what we want. And
there's a lot of effort that goes into
that. But now we're really getting to
the point where it sounds like we're
just a software engineer doing
everything but the coding, cuz we're
defining the tech stack. We're asking
the right questions. We're translating
stakeholder requirements into the
context ecosystem for our coding agent.
There's a lot of work that we have to
put into this. It feels like we're doing
a lot of hand-holding because this
really is what it takes for our coding
agents to be reliable and creating a
system that can be repeatable as well.
Not to mention how important the
validation strategy is for context
engineering as well. Us doing the code
reviews, defining workflows for the
agent to review its own code. Again, so
much of software engineering principles
being built into how we use these coding
agents that people are pretty
universally considering the best
practice right now for working with
these tools. Which by the way, all these
best practices around context
engineering and intent engineering,
getting good results with AI coding
assistants, I teach all of that in the
Agent Coding Course in the Dynamis
community. And so, if you want to learn
how to build a system to get reliable
and repeatable results with AI coding
assistants, definitely check out the
course and the community. This teaches
you how to be the software engineer that
we're saying you need to be right now.
And you don't even have to have a
technical background to get started with
this. But anyway, everything that I
firmly believe in and teach, and what
we're talking about here with this
evolution, and really becoming the
software engineer, this is why I just
can't get behind the statement here that
software engineers are going to go
extinct this year. There's just no way
that it's going to happen.
Now, the second big thing that I wanted
to talk about is the enterprise
adoption. So, like I said, I do a lot of
trainings for teams at larger companies
helping them adopt AI coding assistants.
And there is a very wide range of people
on these teams. There are some that are
super gung-ho about coding agents. They
just want to learn everything. And there
are a lot of, especially senior
engineers, that are very resistant to
these tools because they know the
pitfalls. Large language models
hallucinate. That's never going away. AI
coding assistants introduce a lot of
security issues, actually, in your code
base if you don't have a good system.
And so, if you don't know how to make
that system, and you know the concerns,
it's very hard to adopt these tools,
especially for production enterprise
grade software. Which, by the way,
that's why I love doing these trainings
cuz I teach the system that enables
these larger teams to use AI coding
assistants. But, yeah, I've also seen
how crazy slow the adoption is at
enterprise level because there's so much
corporate red tape. There's procurement
processes, security reviews, engineers
that don't trust the tools in the first
place, like I said. And so, all this
leads to a very slow adoption. And the
other thing to think about is if you
were to go and take the Agent coding
course in Dynamis, you would be
immediately equipped with all of the
rules and commands and skills,
everything that you could apply to
building your own software in just like
1 day. It does not take long to take my
system and use it for yourself. But,
when I come in and do these larger
trainings for companies, 4-hour, even
6-hour workshops I've done before, I
teach the entire system, but they have
to now take that and create a standard
for their entire team. They can't really
use the tools effectively unless
everyone is using them at least in a
pretty similar way. And so, it can take
days, weeks, even months to create this
full system after the training. So,
there's just such a delay. That's why
I'm saying that the adoption is not
going to be that fast for most of these
larger companies.
And of course, I have a ton of data to
back up the things that I've seen
firsthand as well. So, first of all,
there's a survey done in 2025. Out of
all engineering teams, 90% of them now
use AI in their workflow. So, it seems
like a very high percentage, but this
number can mean a lot of different
things cuz there are a ton of companies
out there that they want to be AI
enabled or AI native, whatever they call
it. So, they buy a bunch of licenses for
Claude Code or GitHub Copilot or
whatever, but it's not like their teams
are using them on a daily basis, know
how to actually leverage them. So, 90%
now use AI in their workflows, quote
unquote. Uh but then if we look at the
Stack Overflow survey from last year,
only 51% of professional developers are
actually using AI tools daily. So,
again, this huge disconnect that we
have. And just another stat for this
year, if if I haven't given you enough
already, 76% of executives believe their
teams have embraced AI, while only 52%
of engineers would say the same thing.
The license is available. The company is
AI enabled, but these engineers know
there's so much more they could be doing
with these tools. They're not using them
daily, so they say they're not AI
enabled even though their leadership
says they are. And just one more here,
21% of AI licenses remained
underutilized. So, just continuing to go
with this narrative here where the tools
are becoming available, but they're
really not adopted en masse yet. And
it's going to be so long until it is the
case. And so, yeah, maybe at some point
when we reach AGI, whatever that is,
whenever that is, software engineering
will be dead, but I think that generally
the role of software engineer is just as
protected as a lot of the other roles
that people are scared AI will replace,
but it's just going to take an insane
amount of time for any of that to be a
real concern. I think that's the last
hot take that I have for you here.
So, definitely let me know in the
comments. Now that you've gotten through
everything, what do you think about all
the data that I showed you, my general
thoughts and experiences? I'm I'm
curious if you've seen anything else as
well. And so, the last question I answer
really quickly here is what should we do
about all this? Like, what do I
practically do given all of this
information? Well, the first thing I'd
recommend is never vibe code anything
into production. We have to be the
software engineer coding agents are
capable, very capable, but only with the
right system that we engineer. That also
does mean that it's important to keep
your technical skills sharp. I disagree
with Jensen Huang that kids should not
learn how to code because learning how
to code is very important to be a good
engineer overall, even the skills
outside of coding, and so you can review
the AI-generated code because validation
is also not going away anytime soon. And
then also, just to help you maintain
your code bases. It's good to use your
AI coding assistant as an educator, not
just the coder. If you can work with it
constantly to understand all the
changes, how your code base is evolving,
that prevents you from getting to the
point where you're relying on the coding
agent so much because you really don't
understand all the decisions that it's
made along the way building feature by
feature. You don't want to lose control
of your code base. And even if you're
not vibe coding, you're trying to do a
lot of planning and validating. If
you're not asking the right questions to
understand what it's doing, you're going
to get to the point where you're just
way too reliant on your coding agent.
The people who will thrive are the
engineers that use AI coding assistants
as a force multiplier while still
maintaining a deep understanding of
their craft and their code bases. And
the people who struggle are the ones
that have given up agency completely and
they just crumble when they are no
longer using AI to help them with
anything. Because when AI makes a
mistake, they have no fallback.
So, those are just a couple of points. I
hope that helps you just think about
things you should do right now, how you
should maintain your craft, even using
AI coding assistants to help you be more
technical if you aren't right now. And
so, if you appreciate this video and
you're looking forward to more content
on agentic engineering, concepts around
context engineering and intent
engineering, I would really appreciate a
like and a subscribe. And with that, I
will see you in the next video.